Margaret Mead Christmas card collection, 1962-1977
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
Margaret Mead Christmas card collection
1962-1977
C0216
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
0.25 linear feet (1 folder)
A collection of 11 Christmas cards from noted anthropologist Margaret Mead with five cards signed and with holiday greetings.
Mead, Margaret, 1901-1978
Scope and Content
A collection of 11 Christmas cards from noted anthropologist Margaret Mead with five cards signed and with holiday greetings. The collection includes 10 original photographic prints, with one in color, and one printed card, many taken by friends and contributors to her work, such as visual anthropologist Paul Byers and cinematographer Richard Leiterman. Four of the card images include Mead's granddaughter, Sevanne "Vanni" Kassarjian, with one also showing her daughter, Mary Catherine Bateson (herself a well-respected anthropologist). Three other Christmas cards picture Mead with natives of New Guinea and Bali, often surrounded by children, with one lone color image of her being filmed on Manus Island for the 1968 documentary, "Margaret Mead's New Guinea Journal." Other cards show artwork, a choir, and various children. A charming collection of Christmas cards from one of the world's most renowned anthropologists.
Historical Information
Margaret Mead was a prominent twentieth-century educator, writer, and lecturer. An anthropologist by occupation, she studied the lives of natives of Samoa, Indonesia, and Papua New Guinea. Her first book, "Coming of Age in Samoa: A Psychological Study of Primitive Youth for Western Civilization" (New York: Morrow, 1928), which compared the seemingly care-free adolescent years in Samoan culture to this stressful period of development for American teenagers, catapulted her to instant fame. As she went on to research and write about other cultures, she used her anthropological studies as a framework to discuss and analyze American society.
Related Material
Special Collections & Archives hold the that includes several photographs of Mary Catherine Bateson, Mead's daughter and a former professor of Anthropology at GMU.
The Library of Congress holds the.
Arrangement
Organized by size.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchased in 2012.
Index Terms
Persons:
Mead, Margaret, 1901-1978--Photographs.
Contents List
- Margaret Mead Christmas card collection
  - Two children watching television by Mead with a holiday greeting, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    3" x 5"
  - Mead on Manus Island with native children, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Inscribed by Mead with a holiday greeting. 3" x 4"
  - Mead being filmed on Manus Island for the 1968 documentary "Margaret Mead's New Guinea Journal,", 1967 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Signed by Mead with a holiday greeting. Photograph by Leiterman. 3" x 7"
  - Choir of boys singing at the Petralia Soprana commune in Italy, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    3" x 7"
  - Stone sculpture by William K. Roberts, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mead's granddaughter in a college classroom, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    3" x 6"
  - Baby in a sling, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Photograph by Peter Gordon. 3" x 7"
  - Mead's granddaughter holding cymbals by Mead with a holiday greeting, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Holiday greeting from Mead. 3" x 6"
  - Margaret Mead and her granddaughter in Tehran, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Photograph by Robert Levin. Signed by Mead. 3" x 5"
  - Mead with her daughter, Mary Catherine Bateson, and granddaughter, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Photograph by Polyxane Cobb. 3" x 5"
  - Mead in Bali with children all around, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)